Uh, hi Hector. Hi, Three Jewels. Thank
you for
inviting me to
give a talk. Uh, they're having a
meditation teacher training
in New York City and uh
uh, they asked me to say a few words
about general summary about meditation
and uh
and the message I got Hector was to
you know, we we have lots of trainings
here in Arizona for
uh,
teachers of DCI Global, which is a
business
organization and we have a college
called Sedona College and
uh,
at the end of the term
uh, I have to give them a pep talk
uh,
because there's a
problem with things like uh,
yoga trainings. I I heard a number and I
I heard the number that uh, 80% of the
people
who do a yoga training never teach yoga.
Uh, they just pay their money and and
they learn how to teach and then they
don't get a chance to teach or they
don't they don't take the next step.
Uh, which is they don't become a
teacher. So, uh
I thought uh Hector kind of asked me to
uh,
give you guys some ideas
for your meditation teacher trainees uh,
how to make sure
that you don't waste the training. How
to make sure that you
use it uh, and that you actually teach
people. And I I think
if you don't teach people pretty soon
uh, usually you won't teach people. So,
uh, I'd encourage you guys who just
finished or you're
you're working towards the end of your
meditation teacher training.
Uh,
these are my suggestions as an old
meditator and an old meditation teacher
teacher
uh
about how to teach
and some interesting things that you
might think about
uh as a new meditation teacher
and I think it will make your meditation
teaching more successful
and your meditation more successful. So,
uh here's my
page. I thought first to
talk about how I learned meditation
because uh when I learned meditation 100
years ago
uh
there wasn't any meditation teachers.
And uh we
we
early hippies, we had uh hectares of
late hippy.
Uh
but we early hippies, we didn't have
a chance to meet good meditation
teachers. And in my country, it's not
like Vietnam or something. We don't have
this tradition.
Uh we we don't hardly have the word
meditation.
So, it was hard for me to find teacher.
Here's the first image.
Uh this is Princeton University. I I
went to school there.
And uh
and I there's no meditation at that
time.
Uh you couldn't learn meditation in the
university. Uh but
uh
there was some somebody teaching
meditation in a little house.
Uh like you had to walk a long way
uh and then
they would teach meditation in
somebody's house.
And I uh my friends asked me, "Hey, you
want to
go learn to meditate?" And
I heard about meditation. I didn't know
what it was.
But I was like, "Yeah, I would like to
learn about meditation." My major was uh
Buddhism and Christianity.
And uh Russian and um
Tibetan and Sanskrit.
Uh and then I thought I would like to
uh
you know, learn how to meditate. So, I
went to this
I went to this house
and we all sat down in the living room
and this guy
I I don't know where he learned to
meditate, but
he said, "Okay, I'm going to lead a
meditation."
And then he uh we all we all closed our
eyes.
And in those days, if you sit
cross-legged, you already felt like a
Buddha, you know.
And
so, we all sit down cross-legged and
and then he said, "Close your eyes." And
then we all closed our eyes. And then he
said, "Don't think about anything."
You know,
uh just think about black, you know.
Empty your mind
and don't think about anything and the
whole world is black, you know. And so,
I I
sincerely tried because I never heard
anything about meditation.
And I thought, "Okay, that's
meditation."
And I sat there and we did about 20
minutes
and we were all looking at the black.
And then he said, "Okay,
open your eyes, you know." And then we
we got some
orange juice or something, some
refreshments.
And then he said, "Okay, go home."
And I'm like, "Anything else?" No,
that's it.
You know, and then I went home and I I
remember it was quite a long walk back
to my dormitory and um
and by the time I reached the dormitory,
I decided that was a waste of time.
And uh
you know, if I if I wanted to do that,
we did that every Friday and Thursday
night.
Do you know what I mean? In college
with various things like
Anyway,
I if I want to have a black mind, you
know, I I'm already doing it on the
weekend. So, uh
I didn't see it was a big benefit, you
know.
And I I never tried again for for many
years. I I would say not many, 3 years.
I I didn't try again to meditate. It
just seemed like a waste of time
to me. And then, uh next picture,
uh
I spent As as you guys know here,
I spent 25 years at this uh Mongolian
temple. It's by coincidence, it's about
1 hour from Princeton.
Uh you can drive there in about an hour.
And this is a small
town uh in New Jersey
that was uh
uh I don't know. 700 years ago,
a bunch of Mongolian horsemen uh reached
Europe. They took Vietnam. They took
Afghanistan. They took northern India.
They took
all of Central Asia. They took
uh China.
Uh
started what dynasty, Ming?
Yuan?
Yuan.
Yuan dynasty. And they were very, very
powerful.
And there was Genghis Khan
and his four sons.
And uh they took over the the world.
They killed a half a million They killed
400,000 Austrian soldiers outside of
Vienna.
Uh they took over Moscow. Uh they We
should be speaking Mongolian.
Uh it should be the world's language.
Uh
And then, the Khan died.
And they they had a meeting to to vote
for the new Khan. Mongolians can't agree
on anything.
And they had a big fight and uh
And then, the generals never went back
to Europe.
Uh so,
uh they they left a big group of people
there.
A
a one small general in a in southern
Russia.
And they were living near a river.
And I don't know, 100 years later they
decided to go back home. And uh
the river
was supposed to be frozen. And they had
half their
people on the west side of the river and
half their people on east side of the
river.
And it was Christmas night and the the
day was selected by the Dalai Lama of
that time, like like 17th or something.
And then on that night there was a
strange heat heat wave and the ice
melted in the river.
And the people on the east bank, they
walked back to Mongolia.
And they were
they were ambushed on the way.
And they all died.
Only a handful survived. And so there's
a tiny pocket of Mongolians near the
Gobi Desert.
And they still speak Mongolian.
But the ones on the west side of the
river
they were left behind. And in their
language left behind is Kalmyk.
So nowadays we call them the Kalmyks and
and they have their own country
in southern Russia, Kalmykia.
And it means the left behind ones.
And it's a small Buddhist it's a strange
small Buddhist country in Europe.
And
so we have visitors today from Kalmykia.
Kalmyk and we we were uh
Anyway,
I heard that there was a great teacher,
great meditation teacher living there.
He was sent by the Dalai Lama to to
teach the comics
in New Jersey. So, I went and met him.
He gave a talk at Princeton
uh, on the Heart Sutra and I was so
impressed.
Uh, I asked him if he would teach me.
Uh, here's the Yeah, so he taught me
here.
Uh,
and uh, he taught me for 25 years
at this place and he taught me how to
meditate. He taught me about
100 different meditations. Uh,
which is
what you learn in the Geshe course.
You learn about 100 different
meditations. We talked about it
yesterday
uh, because I would like to record them
uh, before I go to Nirvana. So, um,
we're going to try to do that, okay? Uh,
but anyway, he taught me
extraordinary uh, meditations and
nothing to do with
looking at black in your head or
something, you know?
And and he laughed when I told him I
tried meditating
and he really laughed when I said I was
focusing on black.
And uh,
he called it uh, "Kukpa."
Uh, Kukpa means He said, "Who taught you
that?" I said, "Oh, some guy at
Princeton." He said, "Kukpa." And uh,
Kukpa means idiot. And uh,
he said, "That was an idiot, you know?"
And and he
we had a famous day, the first day I was
there.
Uh, he he he put me in a tiny room.
Uh, you can touch the walls. I sent
Stanley there a couple mon- a month ago
and he checked to see if you can touch
the two walls. Almost.
And uh, he said,
"You can stay here in this room
temporarily."
And I stayed there for 25 years.
And
he he he said, "You can meditate on the
rug here."
You know? And he said, "You try to
meditate
and then you come up and he lived
upstairs
and he told me,
"You come upstairs and tell me how your
meditation is and I'll and I'll give you
suggestion."
So, anyway, the first meditation I did
try to meditate on black.
And then I went up to tell him about my
meditation. He said, "What did you
meditate about?" And I said, "Black."
And he said, "Koopa."
And I I said, "What's Koopa?" He said,
"Idiot."
You know, he said, "Go try again, you
know." And I went back
and I I meditated about this idea I
heard
that nothing is good and nothing is bad,
you know. Like you're supposed to just
relax. If something good happens, don't
be happy.
If something bad happens, don't be
unhappy.
And this is meditation, you know. Then I
So, I did that for like a half hour.
And then he had a bell. He would ring
the bell and that means I'm supposed to
come upstairs
running. I have to run.
For 25 years this was exercise.
And
then I I said, he said, "What did you
meditate about?" I said, "Nothing's
good, nothing's bad." He said, "Shindo
Koopa."
Which means super stupid.
You know,
and
you know, he said,
"If something's nice, it's cuz you
helped somebody. If something's bad,
it's cuz you hurt somebody." Of course,
it's very important to
to meditate about that. And then it went
like that.
The last one I did, he said, "Shindo
Ninai Koopa."
Which means super super stupid.
And then he taught me to meditate and we
worked hard on it. We really really
worked hard on it and he was teaching me
maybe four or five hours a day
for for 25 years and
and it and a lot of the classes were
just the two of us and he taught me to
meditate.
Uh
then I went to next picture.
Uh this is uh
my my monastery in the Himalaya.
And uh so I went there when I had
studied with my teacher for
8 years.
Then he said uh you can
become a monk and you can go to the
monastery.
So uh I would go there about half the
year.
And uh and I and I learned
advanced meditations there. And and we
do them in the Geshe course. So part of
the Geshe course Geshe course is 25
years of study.
And uh I was the first uh American
to finish it and the first Westerner in
my monastery, which is 600 years old.
And we have a very uh
strict uh meditation schedule.
Uh we have to get up like 5:00 and
meditate. It's the first thing you do
every day.
And we meditate together in the morning.
We meditate uh 3,000 people sometimes.
And it's amazing. It's an amazing uh
experience. So I I went deeper in the
meditation there.
And
uh
at the end of my Geshe studies after 25
years, they challenged me
to go to New York and start a business.
Uh and and see if I could apply
uh those
methods to to the real world.
And cuz they didn't have any monk there.
I was the only foreign monk. So they
thought
they'll try an experiment with the
foreign monk, you know.
So they sent me to New York City and I
started a business.
And uh they said
try to see if you can find ways to use
your meditation
uh
to help your business and help normal
people, family people." Cuz they're all
monks.
They rarely go out of the monastery. Um
There's a joke that one of the monks
from our
monastery decided to visit his family
and he had to take a bus,
but he couldn't buy the ticket cuz he
couldn't uh count the money
cuz they don't teach arithmetic. They
don't know how to count, uh which I
discovered later when I did a business
there.
Uh
they lost a lot of money before I closed
it.
We did a secret diamond cutting factory
in inside the monastery.
Wow.
And they lost so much money in 3 years I
had to close it.
Uh
anyway, they're terrible with
with mathematics and and they they don't
They would never use meditation in real
life in the real world. You see what I
mean? And they said,
"You go to New York and you see what you
can do to use meditation in the real
world, you know?" So, I was like,
"Okay."
And it was an interesting uh experiment
because I didn't have any uh
model. I didn't have anyone to help me.
I didn't have anyone to teach me.
I just had to do it on my own and and I
would talk to my teacher every day.
I commuted 2 hours into New York,
Manhattan during the morning, and 2
hours back to the monastery.
I always had to go back to the monastery
at night.
Uh so So, we went I did like that for
over 19 years in corporate life.
And uh I wanted to talk a little bit
about how I used meditation in real life
because I think if you're a meditation
teacher
in this world,
uh Uh, it would probably be most helpful
to teach people how to use meditation in
their real life or in their business
life. So, I thought
uh, I would talk about that. Since you
guys are graduating from your teacher
training
and uh,
these are some suggestions that of what
how I used it, okay? Next picture, you
guys.
This is a typical Geshe debate.
And it's quite physical. Uh, it looks
like uh, martial arts.
And it's it's quite uh,
physical. I uh, Stanley went and talked
to some of my classmates recently and
uh,
and they
they said they told I didn't know. They
told him, "Oh, we had a nickname for
Michael."
And I he said, "What?" And he says, "Are
you among me?" Are you among me means
uh,
the American soldier.
Uh,
cuz I was about 12 in just taller than
every other monk.
Uh,
because they're they're short.
so they called me the because it it's
very helpful in the debate cuz it's very
physical.
You
So, you just push the other guy so
you know, you nobody hits anybody. Like
I in 20 years, 25 years, I never saw
anybody hit anybody.
Uh, I only saw one person get really
angry in in 20 years.
Uh, but there is quite it's quite
physical. And you have to push and and
you have to shove and and you get up and
you do your you do your debate, you
know, like that. So, um,
the reason I show the picture is that
the first kind of meditation
that we use in the monastery
25-year program is called Shargom. Say
Shargom.
And probably you guys learned it there
at the Three Jewels or some variation
from Hector, but Shargom means
you can say a list meditation, a
meditation on a list.
Okay, so Shargum starts
where you memorize
a list of items. Okay, like
uh
I I
you're not allowed
to take a book into the debate room.
Uh everything has to be quoted by
memory.
And we have to quote books. Every debate
you have to quote the book.
You have to quote the book, you know,
and then you have to debate and
and it requires a lot of short-term
memory.
Uh so what you do is you load your mind
for about an hour before the debate.
And we actually it's a beautiful custom.
You walk up to the roof of the building.
And it has a parapet. It has a small
wall.
And you
you pace back and forth. It's very
important when you're memorizing
uh
Shargum.
When you're doing a memorization
meditation, it's great to exercise at
the same time.
You don't sit in a chair or something
like that. You walk back and forth and
try not to fall off the wall. The walls
are short.
And uh
the guys memorizing Shargum, they look
like swimmers. You know how swimmers
they go to the wall and they kick off
and they go back. And they look just
like that. They they look like zip.
And then zip and
and then you memorize for like an hour
a short list. Like you could memorize
the steps of a good meditation.
Or you could memorize the instructions
for meditation. And we memorize
the meditation instructions that were
written
in 750 AD. So that's about
1,200 years ago
by Master Kamalashila. And it's called
Bhavanakrama,
which is the steps of meditation. We
memorize the book
and then we use it for our meditation
and we debated
before we do it.
So,
the idea is that you would know the
theory before you start meditating. You
already know all the theory.
So,
we would do Shargom.
We would do a
a list meditation everyday
before we debate how to meditate. You
see what I mean?
And then you would debate meditating for
weeks or months
and then they would allow you to
meditate. So, you have to know the
theory first. You have to know the
concepts
of meditation before you meditate.
Uh
so, that first kind of meditation,
the kind of the lowest kind,
is Shargom, where you you meditate on a
a a
a list of the steps of meditation,
which is Bhavanakrama, which is the name
of the ancient book.
Uh
then there's a Chegom. Okay, you guys
know Chegom. Chegom means uh
analysis meditation. Sometimes you can
call it uh problem-solving meditation.
Che daw pa ye ten cha da che. It's a
strange spelling if you know Tibetan
word. Good morning.
Uh
he's going to have his class next today.
so, Chegom means
like a problem-solving meditation. It's
still discursive.
You're still talking in your mind and
you're encouraged to talk in your mind.
During a Shargom,
you have to talk in your mind, right?
You have to make a list of concepts or
something.
Then Chegom is also discursive. You are
you are considering
solutions to a problem and then you are
analyzing the It's an analysis
meditation, okay?
And I think in in the Western countries,
in America, where we don't know how to
meditate, and we have no meditation
tradition
in America,
they this idea started that meditation
is uh
empty your mind, or or or imagine the
whole world is black.
And it's wrong somehow to
to think during a meditation. It's wrong
to analyze. It's wrong to consider a
problem and the solutions.
And that's very much against the early
teachings on meditation. A big a big
purpose
of meditation
There's different kinds of meditation.
As I said, maybe a hundred kinds.
But in in Che Gong,
you are certainly considering solutions.
And you're talking to yourself.
And that's very normal and very
encouraged, okay? You have to do that.
And it's a powerful powerful meditation,
okay?
I had a guy I taught
an executive for a DuPont Corporation,
Jeffrey Zoll,
in Asia. He was in charge of human
resources. He started
as a clerk
in the human resources department at
DuPont,
their Asia operations. And he was in
charge of like one person or something.
Later he was in charge of 15,000 people.
And he retired as the head of HR for for
the whole
Asia Pacific.
And he said, I asked him, how did you
get, you know, a hundred promotions like
that? And he said, it's Shargong and
Chergong. You know, every morning he
would do a Shargong.
He would do a meditation on his tasks
for for day.
He would set up his day his business day
and he would prepare
his schedule in his mind
with Shagong. And then he would take the
Shagong and he would look at the
meetings he had or the prob- business
problems he had
and he would do Chegong. He would pause
and do Chegong. He would analyze
uh solutions to business problems
uh during his Shagong. You see what I
mean?
So, he would mix the Shagong and the
Chegong together. And he told me
that's why he was successful in in
DuPont uh corporation.
Just uh Hector, if you're interested.
Uh
his last name is Soul.
And uh I remember he used to take his
vacation time every year when I when I
was there he would be my driver.
Here's this big executive and he would
drive the car.
And we were driving on the highway and I
said, "What is
what does Soul mean?" Like I don't
I never heard this name, you know. They
say
they say half the people in China have
the same five last names or something.
So, family name, Wong, Chen, etc.
But I said I never heard Soul. What does
it mean? And he said, "Oh, Geshe-la, it
means the guy of the left hand.
The the man with the left hand uh which
is very important in our teachings
which you can learn someday, okay? In
Vajrayogini, it's very very important.
Vama Vamamarga, left hand.
So, anyway, uh
that's uh how he used it. So, I had a
problem in the monastery.
Uh
we didn't have any books. We were all
refugees. It was a refugee camp.
And uh the books were destroyed. 15,000
libraries were burned.
Uh all the books were destroyed and we
didn't have copies of the textbooks
for the Geshe course. We didn't have
books.
And uh somebody would memorize a book
and write it out by hand. And and we
would have one copy
for 3,000 people.
You know, and it was a very strange
problem that we didn't have books, you
know.
And
I learned to read
Tibetan books upside down
and backwards because only the teacher
had a book.
And we we were crushed into small little
refugee rooms.
The classes were in tiny rooms and the
teacher would sit on a bed.
And the roof would leak.
And you'd be like duck duck duck. That's
probably what happened to my hair.
And
you know, there'd be a fight in the
students who's going to sit under the
rain, you know.
And
so we learned to read the books upside
down and
and it was a big it was very very very
difficult just to do your lessons
and to memorize what you're supposed to
memorize. And so we had a
business problem, monastery business
problem.
And that was we had to
figure out how to get more books,
you know. And just about that time
the personal computer was invented.
The first personal computers came out.
And I man, I had a chance to at
Princeton
in my Sanskrit classes, I met uh
one of the owners of Hewlett-Packard,
David Packard Jr.
And he had just finished a project to
uh input the classics of Greek.
Uh he input 5,000 classics of Greek.
He paid for it. It was $5 million or
something. And I had a chance to meet
him.
And I said, "Can I interest you in
another project?"
And uh
he said, "No."
Uh he he wouldn't even take the
proposal.
And then uh I have a friend at the
Princeton Library and
Packard had a He has houses everywhere.
I mean, he bought a house in Princeton.
And my friend uh
ha- handed him his wife a proposal
through the kitchen window.
So, they waited outside the Packard's
house.
And then uh the window was open in the
kitchen and the wife was there. And my
friend like handed her He said, "Just
just look at it. Just look at this
proposal, you know." And uh
so, the wife looked at it and liked it.
And she to- she told her husband he had
to meet me. And uh so, he told me he met
me and he said uh "You got 5 minutes
uh to to tell me about your idea, you
know." I took two suitcases of ancient
books.
I took I had these ancient ancient uh
manuscripts
in two suitcases, you know. And I open
up the suitcase. I start showing him the
books, you know.
And why we have to save these books and
why we need the books.
And then he uh he says, "Wait, stop."
After like 10 minutes, he says, "Stop."
And he called his secretary and he said
"Uh cancel all my appointments today.
And this is important." And uh
And he And he's He agreed to do the
project and he built the first input
center. Uh he gave us $30,000. Which was
a lot of money 100 years ago.
Uh
and uh
So, we input the books.
Uh and then we had to do the systems. Uh
he he he invented
the CD-ROM to hold the data.
The CD-ROM was invented by uh David
Packard to hold this data.
And uh and so, we had all these problems
of
search programs,
uh indexing programs, subject
cataloging.
And because in the end there are 300,000
classics of ancient Asia, and it's a
huge
problem of organizing the books. It's
one thing to save them,
but it's a different thing to make them
findable
after you save them, you know.
So, we have very complex
uh indexing programs. We have a very
complex
and very, very fast
search program. It's much faster than
anything available in the world.
Uh
we showed it the other day in in the
translation class.
We looked for something uh and uh it
it'll do about 3 million pages in about
half a second.
And um so, we designed those programs.
Those were all designed
during Chego, okay? I used Chego.
And And that's why I wanted to tell you
about that project. Uh
every every step of the
project, which is 35 years now, and we
have finished uh
about 10% of the target material.
Uh
but everything was developed during
meditation. All of the processes, all of
the
programs, the programming, which is
unique in the world,
uh it was designed during meditations,
okay? So, so for me,
that second kind of meditation, Chego,
uh is extremely is extremely useful.
Here's a Sanskrit. I think next
picture. Here's a Here's a typical
Sanskrit
uh manuscript that we're working with.
These are on palm leaf. That's why
they're shaped like that.
Uh they were
printed before paper was invented. There
was no paper in the world. They used
palm leaf. They scratched the letters
with a needle, and then they fill in the
letters with uh charcoal.
And these have a really good shelf life.
They they last about
1,500 years. A palm leaf will last about
15 centuries.
Paper most paper acidic paper will fall
apart in 200 years or something. So
actually palm leaves are much more
efficient, okay? And um
there's a hole
because that's how they keep the pages
together.
And they put a string through the hole.
They put a hole in the
palm leaf and then they put a string
through the hole and the string is
called in Sanskrit
sutra sutra. So they they call the book
sutra, okay? The book became called
sutra
because the name for string is sutra.
And there you can see the string holes
uh that hold it together. And they last
very well in India even with the
humidity
and hungry bugs.
Um
they they last very well, okay? So
but we had all all this we had a lot of
chigong going on and that's why I
mention it. Problem-solving meditation,
project design meditation.
And it was extremely successful, okay?
And now there's
12 million pages finished
total including scans
and it's online for free.
And and we fundraised and we chigong for
the fundraising.
Okay? You need to
that's when you have a project like that
you need to
problem-solving meditation for how to
get the money
to keep going, you know? And we have we
have survived for 35 years.
Uh we've had hundreds of different
fundraising schemes
and we still survive, okay?
And that's all a result of meditation,
okay? It's a Shargom
and a Chigong, okay? It's using
meditation for problem solving. Next
picture here
is uh this is the Saint Petersburg
Dvorjets.
Uh this Dvorjets means
the palace of the king, of the prince,
of the tsar, okay? This is the old
palace on the river in Saint Petersburg.
Uh after the revolution which took which
started here, the Hermitage is next
door.
They the first shots of the revolution
in the Pochta
uh the post office was where the Lenin
started the revolution.
And uh
they they kicked out the prince and then
they killed the tsar's family and they
put the Tibetan books in the in this
building.
They used it for Sanskrit, ancient
Chinese, ancient Tibetan. They have a
great Dunhuang collection from China.
Uh so we work together with the Dunhuang
Chinese scholars in the same building.
And we spent 12 years here. We spent 12
years in this building.
And it was in the rough times.
Uh the Soviet Union had just collapsed
and there was no funding. There was no
salaries.
And there was no heating.
And Saint Petersburg is the coldest
large city in the world.
And that was hard.
Okay? So uh
but we we did uh use Chigong.
We did problem solve.
We fixed the problem of no books and now
uh
books are very common in the monastery.
Everybody has the whole set of books.
And it came out of it's a business
solution
uh from meditation, okay? And it was
very successful.
And and it still works.
Uh next here
uh we have a translation project.
Uh Now, have finished uh we've we've
been going for 7 years.
Uh including the translations done
before that for the ACI courses.
The ACI courses are 12,000 pages of
translation.
Uh the new translation project is 6,000
pages. So, we have finished 18,000 pages
of very, very difficult technical
translation.
The reason I'm mentioning it is it's an
outcome of the Chego.
It's a It's a It's a It's an outcome of
the solutions
that we found with analysis meditation.
So, this translation project came out of
there. And this particular book called
Emptiness Meditations,
I would say if you're a Three Jewels
meditation teacher graduate
and you don't have this book, you're a
loser.
Uh
okay?
So, uh this is
uh Master Kamala Shila's ancient
Bhavanakrama. Uh this is the original
book of meditation for all of Asia.
And uh he taught
very unusual at his time in the 8th
century,
1,200 years ago, he taught in
India, Tibet, and China. He He taught He
He traveled widely.
And he taught this book three times.
He had three versions of the book.
Uh he had one version for India, one
version for
West China, and one version for Central
China.
And then he would teach it differently
to different people. So, there's three
Bhavanakramas.
And we found all three, we photographed
all three, we input all three, and we
chose the best one for Westerners.
And we translated it, and it's in this
book, okay? And uh
So, this book has a a long couple
hundred pages on how to do emptiness
meditations.
And then it has a couple hundred pages
on meditation technique, whatever you
use it for. Shamatha, vipashyana,
and tonglen. We didn't talk about
tonglen yet, um,
but that's a
fixed meditation, fixation meditation.
And we'll talk about that, okay? But in
the meantime,
if you're going to be a meditation
teacher,
I would I would I would encourage you to
get this book. It's a It's uh available
by by ebook
uh
and you know, you can get it from what's
it called? Diamond Cutter Press
uh
in a few in a in a minute or two, you
can get a copy.
And you should
live
we call live, sleep, and breathe this
book, you know? If you're going to teach
meditation,
uh you should
I put a copy of this book on my kitchen
table.
And I don't let myself have a coffee
unless I read a couple pages.
So therefore, I'm reading it all the
time.
Okay? So, you know, if you're going to
teach meditation,
uh you should have it. Now, uh my
monastery gave me a another job. They
said, "We wanted you to prove
that you can use shamatha, vipashyana,
tonglen, the three kinds of meditation
in a business situation. Can you start a
business
in Manhattan?" They sent me back to
Manhattan
and they said, "Can you start a a
business using these three kinds of
meditation as the main business model,
especially for innovation, for
creativity?"
And they said, "We want you to explore
the
application
of Kamala Shila's three kinds of
meditation
uh in business and especially in being
creative
and in coming up with new business
solutions."
So, here's the
here's the
This is our building, okay? We we with
three people, we borrowed $50,000.
And by using
meditation,
especially problem-solving meditation,
and there's a special version that I
developed in the business, which I'll
teach you
today. Okay?
We developed from three people to 10,000
people.
We became the largest diamond jewelry
company in the world, and we sold it to
Warren Buffett in 2009 for a quarter
billion dollars.
Okay? And the meditation helped a lot.
Okay? So,
for innovation, I think what made us
number one in the world, there's about
100,000 competitors
in the world. We're number one.
And I think it was meditating. I think
it was meditation. So, we're going to
talk about
By the way, I have 5 minutes, Hector, I
know. Then we're supposed to do Q&A.
Usually Geshe la runs into the Q&A.
Uh
Okay.
He knows me. Uh and we're good friends
for a long, long time.
Uh
So, we I wanted to talk about a special
kind of application
of meditation
that we used a lot in my company. And I
would say we built the company on this
kind of meditation. It's a It's a
variation
on problem-solving meditation. It's a
che gum.
And we use it specifically for
innovation. Okay? One of the most
frustrating things in the world
is to try to think of something new, and
your brain is not cooperating, you know?
Like, you sit on the toilet seat,
and you say, "I got to think of a new
idea."
And then it just doesn't come, you know?
I don't You know, it seems like the when
you have a good idea,
when you have an innovative idea in a
business,
it's not controllable. You it's not on
demand. You cannot do creativity on
demand. It seems like
you just have to wait until the idea
comes. Sometimes I jump up from the
toilet and run around the house looking
for a pen and paper.
And my wife's like, "Are you okay?"
You know, I got to find a pen, you know,
I got this idea. I'm afraid I'm going to
forget.
And
a lot of times creativity is
uncontrollable.
Uh you don't have any creative idea for
3 months.
And then suddenly in one sitting,
uh
you come up with five good ideas, you
know. I don't know why.
But wouldn't it be more convenient
if the creativity came
kind of when you're at the office
instead of in the other office? And
Okay. So, uh
I I wanted to explain or talk about
the method that I developed during my my
working years, 19 years in Manhattan.
And here's the next picture.
This is a cabin in Oak Creek Canyon.
It's on the way to the Grand Canyon.
It's the second largest canyon in the
United States. It's about
half an hour from our business office in
Sedona.
It's a half an hour from our offices,
and it's a beautiful beautiful canyon.
It's the second largest in the in the
United States.
And uh this is a cabin that I go to.
And this is a special kind of meditation
that we learn to do
uh
for innovation. And this is was taught
to me by my teachers. We call it circle
day.
And uh we
they encourage us
when you're looking for a new solution
to a business problem, when you're
looking for a creative invention, you
know, to invent something
on schedule is extremely difficult, you
know? Ideas come in the toilet. Ideas
come just before you wake up in the
morning and then you can't remember
them.
And it seems like
the process of creativity or new ideas
is not controllable. But if you learn
this special kind of
examination meditation Qigong,
I'm going to propose to you a process
by which you can learn how to
have ideas on demand, creativity on
demand.
So I wanted to and and I I would say
first of all
find a
find a quiet place to
to do an innovation meditation and don't
let it be your house, okay? Your house
is loaded up, your apartment is loaded
up with uh
reminders of your daily life.
And it's too distracting, okay? You
cannot do creativity meditation in your
house. Your apart- apartment or your
house, forget it.
Okay? There's too much
collected junk there
that that distracts you and and it
actually prevents you
from being creative, okay? To To try to
sit in your normal space
where you live and eat and and raise
your children
is is almost impossible to come up with
real innovation, okay?
So
I'm going to mention one business
problem that I had
and I used Qigong in my company
and I believe that's why we became
number one, okay? We We invented
many many business processes
that are used in the jewelry industry
Uh,
and we we invented them
by going to the cabin.
Uh,
and it you can't just go to a cabin and
sit there and and think your your
innovation is going to come. You need
training.
And you need a program. And that's why
um Kamlesh Shukla's text is so
important. It gives you a structure
for an innovation meditation, okay? So,
uh I would take uh Baman Acharya, I
would take Kamlesh Shukla's book with
me. I would go to the cabin
and I would do meditations, creativity
meditations.
And I I wanted to describe them.
And uh I'll say more about it. We are
we have developed uh programs for
business people. We teach about 138,000
business people a year.
Uh and we teach them these kind of
meditations. And we have a special
program which I'll tell you about
uh which is creativity retreats or
innovation retreats for business people
or art artists, musicians. We had a
a a well-known musician here last night.
Uh it was fun.
Uh and so we have a creativity retreat
program for for artists, uh musicians,
business people.
And we And I'll I'll tell you roughly
what we teach them, but it takes time.
Uh
So, my business problem, one of I had
thousands of business problems.
Everybody says, "Oh, gosh, how did you
build this
huge company and and sold it to Warren
Buffett." And
but every single day was a fight.
You know, if you've been in a corporate
life,
it's it's not easy, okay? It's not like
you're sitting there with a
a good
coffee and
and at 9:00 the good idea comes and at
10:00 you go golfing or something like
that. It it's not like that. Business is
a
is a constant
challenge.
And problems happen all day. And I don't
care who you are
and I don't care how many years you
spent in the GIA course,
uh
you go to the office and within 10
minutes there's three problems.
And it goes like that the whole day.
It's like having three kids, right?
So, uh
here's a typical problem, okay? Uh we
needed
we we had a lot of customers in Japan
and we needed uh pastel color. Pastel
colors means bright spring colors, like
bright green, bright red,
you know, bright yellow. We needed
different kinds of gemstones
that were pastel colors and we couldn't
find a blue one.
We couldn't find a It has to be the
right price. What's the right price?
For black, we use onyx, okay? Onyx costs
25 cents.
We developed a special cutting method in
Korea. Don't tell anybody.
We developed it through a a chigo.
We And we took a 25 cent
black black onyx and we did special
cutting on it and we sold them for $900.
That's a bit of a profit.
Okay? And
if you know how to do innovation
meditation,
uh
you can invent
unique products that nobody else knows
how to make. So, here's a product
that uh This is uh brown topaz.
Uh the color I describe as pee pee color
on a bad day.
Bad day pee pee color.
And uh this is from Sri Lanka. The the
main supplies come from Ratna Dweepa,
the jewel island,
uh ancient jewel island of Ceylon or Sri
Lanka.
And this is a natural color of natural
topaz.
And we were struggling
to find a light blue stone. And there
was nothing in the world
that was good that we could use.
Sapphire was too expensive.
Uh and sapphire didn't come
in a pastel color. So, I took this
problem into my meditation cabin.
I I took this problem. We need to turn
uh
bad PT color
Is it possible? And we knew from
experience
that in nature there is a genetic
um what do you call it? Exception for
topaz structure
where it turns light blue. It turns into
a stunning color, but very rare. Very
very rare. So, we studied the structure.
We went into the cabin.
We did our
uh check-in process, innovation,
creativity on demand
uh
system meditation. And I worked on it in
meditation.
And here's the result.
And uh okay.
That's a uh that comes in two colors
called Swiss blue and sky blue. We
helped invent the process.
It's secret. I'm not going to tell you.
Uh
but I can tell you that the stone costs
$1.25.
And uh the finished stone is about $900.
Okay. And the rest is just profit.
And that's how you make the largest
jewelry company in the world. Uh
and
and that process was
invented through meditation. Okay. And
that innovation and it was a planned
innovation, which is something you don't
usually have. Usually you're sitting in
your toilet hoping for an innovation.
Or you know, just before you wake up you
get an idea and you forget it.
Right? You tell your wife, "Honey, I got
to write this down." She's like, "Well,
we got to have coffee." And you're like,
"Oh, man, I can't remember."
And instead of that,
um we have a
We have a process. We and we have
developed it, okay? We have done
innovation meditation on innovation
meditation.
Okay? And we have innovated it.
And we got it down to an interesting
system. And it's a We have a colleague
from Shenzhen, China, Stanley Chen. He's
here.
And he's in charge of this project. Uh
it's his business.
Uh it's a innovation retreats.
Uh how to use how to
how to market or how to train business
people
and then how to guide them
in an actual innovation retreat. So, we
have a retreat center here
in in Arizona. We have other centers
around the world that we use uh in
different countries.
And Stanley is in charge of this
project.
And it's Do you have a name for it yet?
I don't know. Innovation retreats.
We got to do an innovation retreat on
that.
And uh
And And I would say one thing. So,
Hector, I know that you're training
people there. You described to me
and I'll just say it frankly. He said,
"Look, Geshe La, the people in the
meditation teacher training,
they're kind of two kinds of people. One
is kind of spiritual people. And they
want to learn meditation and and learn
it for their personal development.
And to help other people with their
personal development. And then the
second kind are kind of like business
people. They want innovation. They want
creativity.
Maybe they are artists of some kind.
And they want They want innovation.
Uh so, I would say that uh
you can you can
We We don't say kill two birds with one
stone. We say you can feed two deers
with one apple.
Okay? And uh
And uh Stanley's working on this
project. And I would say that uh
Hector, if you have graduates I'm
thinking of Rachel for some reason.
Rachel Webb the who who who runs the
Three Jewels there.
Uh
I think Rachel and Stanley I think you
would be a good uh
team
to uh
I think if if Rachel contact Stanley
or or you guys in the teacher training
there in the meditation teacher
training, if you're interested,
uh
it would be fun to organize some
creativity retreats together and start
to offer them to business people. We
have again uh last year
we trained 138,000
business people in 20 countries.
And um it I think it'd be wonderful
if And that's a practical use of a
meditation teacher training. That means
80% of the teachers are not going to be
unemployed.
110% of them are going to be busy
like at Diamond Mountain. Okay? So uh
Next picture uh
This is the original Diamond Cutter
book. Uh
somebody asked me
the largest publisher in the world um
well who was it at the time?
Random House. Uh they asked me to
Double Day, Random House, which was
bought bought by Random House.
Uh they asked me to write a book about
how to do these creativity retreats.
There's a chapter in this book, you can
read it. We just finished a 20th
20th anniversary edition. Uh it's been
published in 35 languages or something
like that. So if you're interested, you
can read that one.
Uh
here's a typical
uh creativity meditation class in
Vietnam, okay?
And it's 1,500 people in Is it Ho Chi
Minh, I think?
Uh,
and they are studying like
creativity and how to use meditation for
inventing new processes.
So, I encourage you guys to, uh,
to do it there. And last picture here
and then I'll finally shut up.
This is a special group of 74
inventors.
And and they meet at MIT University, MIT
Business School once a year.
And they all graduated from MIT Business
School.
And they're old. I mean, they they
graduated 20 years ago or something.
And, um,
and they meet at the Business School of
MIT once a year.
And it's a secret meeting. It's a
closed-door meeting. They have 74 people
and they will not take a seat in the
group. There are 6,000 people waiting
for one of them to die.
Okay?
Like, if a seat becomes available. And
they just made a rule they will not
allow more people in the room.
And, uh, and then if you They asked me
to go speak there.
And, uh, I had to sign a contract that I
wouldn't, uh,
I wouldn't repeat anything I heard to
other people because they are all
inventors. They are 74
inventors, creative people.
And they are inventing amazing stuff
that will change our world and it
includes
I so I take my signature very seriously.
Anyway, it includes medical
applications, very very exotic medical
applica- applications. And, uh,
garbage process, can you believe that?
Okay, one guy's working on a machine.
You throw garbage in it at this end of
the building, and by the time it gets to
that end of the building, it's finished
bars of metal and paper rolls and
take normal garbage,
throw it into a box,
and at on the other side of the room,
you have finished rolls of paper,
finished bars of metal.
You know, you just throw garbage into
it.
And then they're doing quite well. Okay.
So, I would say
uh these are the kind of things that
we'll be doing here.
Uh next picture.
This is our uh retreat center. This is
where we'll be doing the first
innovation retreat. It's all set up.
It's a thousand acres. It's the largest
retreat center
in the United States.
We have
cut We can fit a hundred people
uh in an innovation conference, and we
would like to hold innovation
conferences here. Stanley Chen is in
charge of that.
Here's what our cabin looks like. Next
picture.
Uh and this is what the what the place
looks like, right? And uh we have built
about 30 or 35 cabins like this.
And it's very, very good for creativity
retreat.
Uh if you're hardcore
and you want a deep retreat, you get a
next
a yurt.
And I I spent three years in a retreat
in a yurt silent for three years. And
this my yurt This is not my yurt, but
this is exactly the sister of my yurt.
And
you can do a deep, deep meditation,
deep, deep retreat on creativity. So, we
have the facilities here.
Uh we have a director of the of the
program. It's his company. He He's
building the company.
Uh,
it's his baby.
Uh, he owns it. And I think, um,
it would be a very, very interesting
project, uh, to get involved with. So,
if you meditation teacher trainees in
New York, if if you're not drinking
coffee,
uh,
you
Hey, I lived there for
a long time.
Uh, you might get in touch with Danny
and you guys will work on it, okay?
Uh,
okay, last thing.
this is called Jogom, okay? Jogom is a
meditation that we did not talk about
yet.
And it's a called a fixation meditation
or spiritual spiritual meditation, okay?
And if I'm going to talk to some
great meditation training
trainees, okay? If I'm going to give
them advice,
here's my last advice, okay?
Every person you ever teach meditation
and every meditation teacher
will die.
Okay? That's
That's how business goes. All businesses
die.
All people in all businesses die.
Okay? And we got to get ready for it,
okay? So, there's a certain time
in your business career
when you should transition
to deeper things, okay? You should do
the final creativity, the final
innovation,
which is how to die in a different way,
okay? And and how to apply these ideas
to human life and and the problems of
peace on this earth.
You know, in the end,
uh,
our meditation practice has to go
deeper. I support creativity
meditations. I use them for 20 years,
you know,
but in them at the same time
as you go through your meditation
teacher training,
you must consider
uh, using meditation for deeper
purposes, okay?
And you will not live forever. No
business ever lasted forever. No
innovation ever lasts forever.
And and things pass, people get old, and
and you have to
uh, use your meditation. You have to be
ready to use the same techniques for
deeper purposes. And it's not a
spiritual thing, and it's not a
religious thing. It's a human thing. If
you're a human being,
you will get old, and you you will
finish your business career,
and and you will be sitting there
telling people about innovations you did
20 years ago.
Okay? And uh,
I say,
uh,
feed two deers with one apple.
You know, get your meditation skills
well developed, uh, develop your
meditation ability, and when it's the
proper time, we call sannyasi in ancient
India. When you make that transition
from your business life
to your later life, and as you prepare
for death yourself,
then wouldn't it be wonderful to have
special meditations for that?
And special meditations that will guide
you on.
And they deve- they come out of
the shargon,
the the list meditation, go to chegon
innovation meditation, and then graduate
to jogon uh, in your later life
to where you are innovating ways to die,
or ways to move on. What happens us
after we die and where do we go?
Uh
we go somewhere, okay?
And it would be if you know you're going
to take a trip, you should pack a bag.
I'm packing tonight cuz we're leaving
tomorrow.
And the same thing with your life, okay?
Like do your business innovations,
make a big company, sell it to Warren
Buffett,
uh but learn the meditations that are
going to continue on after your business
life. And everyone makes that journey.
And I think a meditation teacher
training is not complete unless you
prepare the meditations that you need.
And I don't think they're more important
or
you know, life is important. Uh it's
it's important to be able to invent new
stuff.
And it's important to invent a new life
when you die.
And uh it's just a continuation. It's
all the same process, okay? Uh and so I
I think we should balance these uses of
meditation. Last thing
that I You said last thing I
In In Mexico they call me Señor Última
Cosa,
uh which means Mr. Last Thing.
Um
one of the greatest meditations I've
ever learned, we call it coffee
meditation, and that's uh I think
as a teacher trainee at Three Jewels,
you should never
uh
fail
to teach coffee meditation. Maybe it
should be the last thing in a 1-hour
talk.
You should always spend a few minutes on
coffee me- Coffee meditation means
at the end of the day,
after you're in bed, after you put your
head on the pillow,
as you fall off to sleep, which
psychologically is a very important
time,
because subconsciously your mind will
cook it for 6 hours, 7 hours, 8 hours.
Uh
it's it's an ancient meditation
tradition
as you fall off asleep
to think about
the good things you have done to serve
other people today.
Okay? Positive reinforcement. Okay? Yes,
you're a selfish guy. Uh-huh, yeah. Yes,
you're lazy.
Uh yes, you got upset and angry at a lot
of people today.
Yeah, but you did some good stuff, also.
A few.
And uh
it's extremely important
uh to fall asleep
considering the healthy and and
charitable
and kind things you have done to today.
It's very important never
to go to sleep thinking something
negative.
And and if I was going to
give my last word to some teacher
trainees from New York
uh
I would say uh
always end a always end a meditation
session with
with this coffee meditation. Always
always teach people to fall asleep
correctly
in meditation.
Uh and then all night long uh it's
reinforcing this kind of positive
behavior. Again, if you're interested in
the creativity
retreat co-innovation retreat program,
talk to Stanley Chen. We're going to put
up his
email, I guess.
Uh
you guys have it? Francisco?
Yeah.
And uh I I have this dream that uh
Hector, your your people uh Rachel comes
to mind. I don't know why.
Uh just cuz we we had a chance to meet
recently, but um
but I I think uh there I think these
people in
the people in your teacher training and
Stanley
by the way, who has a very successful
business program for Chinese executives
uh called China
for a classic software.
Uh
a very very successful program
for innovation with Chinese business
executives. And I could see
uh the New Yorkers
coming from the East Coast of the US and
these Chinese business executives who
are
high-powered, very high-powered, and
very excited people.
Uh
that they could come from
Asia
and you guys could meet halfway, which
is exactly Diamond Mountain.
And uh uh
And in my experience, in how many years
we've been doing that?
We've been doing 7 years of executive
training in China.
Uh it's extremely
successful, and we have very very
successful people coming out of that
program.
Uh so I think uh I would encourage
grandpa
would like to see his kids get together.
And uh I have great We have great
teachers from China,
Asia, and we have great teachers from uh
New York. And uh personally, I'd like to
see you guys I think if you did
something together
through this uh can you put the email up
again?
Uh
I think it would be interesting. I'm
looking forward to see the results.
Hector, uh thank you for asking me to
talk. I'm sorry I went too long.
And uh
see you next time. And thank you very
much.